Inventory of the Reetika Vazirani Papers 1967-2008
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Reetika Vazirani Papers 1967-2008 1982-2003
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2008.122
4.00
This collection contains the personal and professional papers of Reetika Vazirani. It includes a number of poems, manuscripts, photographs, floppy disks, correspondence and publications that relate to her work as a published writer and instructor. The collection also holds personal correspondence, a sketchbook, and legal documents, as well as materials regarding Vazirani's death and legacy.
Vazirani, Reetika, 1962-2003 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Box 8 is restricted until 2018 and Box 9 is restricted until 2043. All other portions of the collection are open to researchers. Consult a staff member for details.
Biographical Note
Reetika Gina Vazirani was born August 9, 1962 in Patiala, India. In 1967, her family moved to the United States and settled in Silver Spring, Maryland. After high school, Vazirani earned her bachelor's degree from Wellesley College in 1984. She studied creative writing at Boston University from 1987 to 1988, and graduated with a master's degree in Fine Arts from the University of Virginia in 1997.
Vazirani published a number of essays and poems in anthologies, literary reviews, and journals. Many of her writings drew on her experiences as an Indian immigrant, and she earned critical recognition for her work. Her first book, "White Elephants" (Beacon Press, 1996), was awarded the Barnard New Women Poets Prize, and her second book, "World Hotel" (Copper Canyon Press, 2003), won a Anisfield-Wolf Book Award. Vazirani also served as a contributing and advisory editor on the literary magazines "Shenandoah" and "Callaloo."
Vazirani was also an experienced teacher, having taught creative writing and poetry at a number of universities. She began as a poetry instructor at the University of Virginia in 1996, and served as a visiting assistant professor at the University of Oregon a year later. In 1998, Vazirani accepted the position of the Margaret Banister Writer-in-Residence at Sweet Briar College in Virginia. She briefly taught as a visiting faculty member at the College of New Jersey in 2001. From 2002 to 2003, she served as Writer-in-Residence for the College of William and Mary.
Reetika Vazirani committed suicide on July 16, 2003 in Chevy Chase, Maryland. She was 40 years old.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the personal and professional papers of Reetika Vazirani. It includes a number of poems, manuscripts, photographs, floppy disks, correspondence and publications that relate to her work as a published writer and instructor. The collection also holds personal correspondence, a sketchbook, and legal documents, as well as materials regarding Vazirani's death and legacy.
Arrangement of Materials
The collection is organized into the following series and sub-series: Series 1: Biographical Materials, 2000-2003
Series 2: Career, 1982-2003, including Sub-series 1: Publishing, 1996-2003; Sub-series 2: Literary Journals and Writing Workshops, 2000-2003; Sub-series 3: Teaching, 2000-2003; Sub-series 4: Poetry Readings and Job Searches, 1999-2003; Sub-series 5: Colleagues, 2000-2003; Sub-series 6: Correspondence, 2002-2003
Series 3: Personal and Professional Letters and Work, 1985-2006, including Sub-series 1: Background on Miller, 2003; Sub-series 2: Correspondence, 1985-2003; Sub-series 3: Miscellaneous Professional Materials, 1989-2003; Sub-series 4: Death, Funeral, Legacy, 2003-2006
Series 4: Personal Papers and Materials, 1973-2008 including Sub-Series 1: Financial Records, 1981-2005; Sub-series 2: Correspondence, 1993-2003; Sub-series 3: Personal Information and Records, 1973-2003; Sub-Series 4: Articles, Memorials, Condolences, 2003-2008
Series 5: Miscellaneous Career and Personal Items, 1967-2003.
Additional Information
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements
Electronic records which are part of this collection require a computer with appropriate software for viewing.
Related Materials
University Archives Faculty-Alumni File Collection
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
College of William and Mary--Dept. of English
Topical Term:
East Indian Americans--Poetry; Women--United States--Poetry
Detailed Description of the Collection
  Series 1: Biographical Materials
- Biographical Materials, 2000-2003
  This series contains documents that provide a general overview of Reetika Vazirani's personal and professional life. Contents include her resume, brief biographies, a photograph, a magazine profile, and obituaries.
  - (1)
    - Resumes and biographical information (with photo), 2000-2003 (1)
      This folder includes five versions of Vazirani's resume as well as two brief biographical descriptions, probably for promotional use.
    - "How to Leave and Where to Stay: traveling with Reetika Vazirani," from Poets and Writers Magazine (12 photocopies), January/February 2003 (1, 2)
      This folder contains 12 photocopies of a profile on Vazirani written by Renee H. Shea and published in Poets and Writers Magazine. The article contains images and extensive background information.
    - Poets and Writers (2 copies), January/February 2003 (1, 3)
      This folder contains two copies of an issue of Poets and Writers Magazine published in January 2003. It includes a a profile on Vazirani written by Renee H. Shea that contains images and extensive background information (pages 38-44).
    - Obituaries, July 2003 (1, 4)
      This folder contains multiple newspaper and photocopied versions of Reetika Vazirani's obituary. She died July 16, 2003.
  Series 2: Career
- Career, 1982-2003
  This series contains documents relating to Vazirani's work as a poet, writer, and instructor. Contents include materials relating to publishing, teaching, writing, and poetry readings, as well as a number of letters and emails from colleagues.
  Note: Additional materials concerning Vazirani's career, including floppy disks, a journal, and a set of index cards, are located in Box 10 of the collection.
    Subseries 1: Publishing
  - Publishing, 1990-2003 (1)
    This sub-series includes materials concerning Vazirani's efforts to publish her work. It includes calls for authors, acceptances and rejections for her work, correspondence with publishers, and publicity materials for her books, "White Elephants" and "World Hotel." Also included are notes and drafts of poems and uncompleted manuscripts. Some of the documents are not dated.
    Note: Box 10 of the collection contains a set of index cards dated from 1990 to 2003, with details on publishing submissions and contact information.
    - (1)
      - Calls for Authors, Acceptances, Rejections, 1998-2003 (1, 5)
        This folder includes calls for poetry and author participation, as well as acceptance and rejection letters in regards to publishing Vazirani's work.
      - "White Elephants I," from "White Elephants" (3 copies), 1996 (1, 6)
        Contains copies of a hand-written version of the poem "White Elephants I" from Vazirani's book of the same title, "White Elephants."
      - Copper Canyon Press and Publishing of World Hotel, 2002-2003 (1, 7)
        This folder contains a range of emails and letters concerning the publication and promotion of Vazirani's second book, "World Hotel," by Copper Canyon Press.
      - Interviews for "World Hotel", 2003 (1, 8)
        This folder includes a questionnaire and transcript of an interview with Vazirani on her book, "World Hotel."
      - Publisher's Weekly review on "World Hotel" (19 copies), 2003 (1, 9)
        This folder contains copies of the January 20, 2003 edition of Publisher's Weekly review on Vazirani's book, "World Hotel."
      - "World Hotel" Reviews and Notes, 2002-2003 (1, 10)
        This folder contains a range of reviews of "World Hotel," as well as notes made by Vazirani.
      - Anisfield-Wolf Book Awards, 2003 (1, 11)
        This folder contains information and notes regarding Vazirani winning the Anisfield-Wolf Book Award for "World Hotel."
    - (1, 2)
      - Beacon Press Correspondence, 2002-2003 (1, 2)
        This folder contains contact information and correspondence between Vazirani and Beacon Press.
      - Miscellaneous Publishing Correspondence, 2002 (1, 2)
        This folder contains faxes and letters regarding the publishing of Vazirani's various works in 2002.
      - Miscellaneous Publishing Correspondence, 2003 (1, 2, 3)
        This folder contains faxes and letters regarding the publishing of Vazirani's various works in 2003.
      - Labeled "Manuscript in Progress", 2001-2002? (1, 2, 4)
        Vazirani labeled the contents of this folder as "Manuscript in Progress." A portion of the poems are not dated.
      - Poem Drafts and Notes for "Whole", 2001-2003 (1, 2, 5)
        This folder contains drafts and notes concerning an unpublished compilation of poems Vazirani titled "Whole."
      - Poem Drafts and Notes labeled "Vanishing Cream", undated (1, 2, 6)
        This folder contains drafts of poems and notes for a compilation Vazirani titled "Vanishing Cream."
      - Poem Drafts and Notes labeled "Truth Serum", undated (1, 2, 7)
        This folder contains drafts of poems and notes for a compilation Vazirani titled "Truth Serum."
      - Notes and Drafts, undated (1, 2, 8)
        This folder contains a range of undated notes and drafts by Vazirani.
    Subseries 2: Literary Journals and Writing Workshops
  - Literary Journals and Writing Workshops, 2000-2003 (2)
    This sub-series includes information, correspondence, and applications for literary journals and writing workshops Vazirani wrote for and participated in. Such workshops include the San Miguel Poetry Week, Callaloo, Bennington, and Struga Poetry Evenings.
    - (2)
      - "Catamaran" Emails, 2002-2003 (2, 9)
        This folder contains emails relating to Vazirani's involvement in Catamaran, a journal for South Asian literature.
      - Schedule for San Miguel Poetry Week, 2002 (2, 10)
        This folder includes the schedule for the San Miguel Poetry Week, in which Vazirani participated.
      - Callaloo Correspondence and Reviews, 2000-2003 (2, 11)
        This folder contains emails, a letter, a fax, and reviews pertaining to Vazirani's work on the literary journal "Calloloo."
      - Callaloo Creative Writing Workshops, 2003 (2, 12)
        This folder contains information and materials on the Callaloo Creative Writing Workshop that Vazirani attended at Texas A&M University in May, 2003.
      - Bennington Writing Workshop, 2003 (2, 13)
        This folder contains faculty and travel information and a copy of a poem from the Bennington Writing Workshop that Vazirani attended in June 2003.
      - Struga Poetry Evenings Application, 2003 (2, 14)
        This folder contains email invitations, information, and an application for the Struga International Poetry Evenings Festival that was held in Macedonia in August 2003.
      - Yaddo Artists' Community, 2003 (2, 15)
        This folder contains a thank you letter and two application forms (one partially completed, one left blank) for the Yaddo Artists' Community in Saratoga Springs, New York.
      - Labeled "Craft lecture, Centrum, Sherman Alexie", undated (2, 16)
        This folder contains lecture notes and poetry originally organized and labeled by Vazirani.
    Subseries 3: Teaching
  - Teaching, 2000-2003 (3)
    This sub-series contains materials relating to teaching positions Vazirani held at Sweet Briar College and the College of William and Mary. It includes student writing exercises, course instructor evaluations, and course syllabi and notes.
    - (3, 2)
      - Student Writing Exercises for "Fiction" Course, 2000 (3, 2, 17)
        This folder contains the results of a class assignment asking for student-suggested ideas for writing exercises. They are from a course on fiction Vazirani taught in the summer of 2000.
      - William and Mary Employment, 2002-2003 (3, 2, 18)
        This folder contains materials related to Vazirani's position as Writer-in-Residence at William and Mary. Included are course evaluations, faculty contact information, letters, an appeal to the Parking Committee, and information concerning her residence at the Heritage Inn.
      - Advanced Creative Writing Course on Michael Ondaatje: Syllabi and Notes, 2003 (3, 2, 19)
        This folder contains syllabi and notes for the English 470 writing course on Michael Ondaatje Vazirani taught at William and Mary in the Spring of 2003.
      - William and Mary Descriptive Linguistics: Syllabus and Reading, 2003 (3, 2, 20)
        This folder contains the syllabus and a reading assignment for the English 405/Anthropology 430 Descriptive Linguistics course held in Spring 2003.
    Subseries 4: Poetry Readings and Job Searches
  - Poetry Readings and Job Searches, 1999-2003 (4)
    This sub-series contains information regarding poetry reading events Vazirani participated in, as well as resumes, letters, and applications concerning teaching positions.
    - (4, 3)
      - Poetry Reading Requests and Information, 2001-2002 (4, 3, 1)
        This folder contains emails relating to various poetry readings given by Vazirani on her work.
      - Poetry Reading Requests and Information, 2003 (4, 3, 2)
        This folder includes letters, emails, brochures, and notes concerning the readings Vazirani gave and scheduled to give in 2003.
      - Smith College Poetry Reading, 2003 (4, 3)
        This folder contains various promotional materials for a reading Vazirani gave at Smith College on March 11, 2003.
      - Job Search Materials, 1999-2003 (4, 3)
        This folder includes letters, resumes, letters of recommendation, and requests for references for multiple jobs Vazirani was interested in and persued.
      - Emory University Correspondence and Information, 2002 (4, 3, 5)
        This folder contains materials relating to a teaching position at Emory University in Atlanta, Georgia that Vazirani accepted, then later declined.
      - Barnard Poet Search, 2003 (4, 3, 6)
        This folder includes three copies of Vazirani's application for a teaching position at Barnard College in New York City, as well as correspondence confirmation they were recieved.
    Subseries 5: Colleagues
  - Colleagues, 1982-2003 (5)
    This sub-series contains contact information, articles, promotional materials, and letters relating to colleagues and friends of Vazirani.
    - (5, 3)
      - Emails, Online Biographies, and Poet Directories, 2002-2003 (5, 3, 7)
        This folder contains materials relating to Vazirani's network of colleagues and publishers, as well as brief online biographies about her.
      - Email Addresses, 2001-2002 (5, 3, 8)
        This folder contains lists of email addresses and contact information collected by Vazirani.
      - Papers from Book Accession, 1987-2003 (5, 3, 9)
        This folder contains papers removed from the accession of books included in the Vazirani collection. They range from promotional materials for poets Paul Muldoon, Marilyn Hacker, and Rita Dove, biographical information on Yusef Komunyakaa, a photocopy of "The Light of the World" by Derek Walcott, a copy of an introduction for Czeslaw Milosz, to an autograph by Seamus Heaney. Also included is an untranslated document removed from a book written in an unidentified language at this time (4/20/09).
      - "Clio Rising" by Joel Brouwer, Poetry in Review vol. 21, issue 1, 2002 (5, 3, 10)
        This folder contains a copy of "Clio Rising" faxed in February 2003, with notes.
      - Letter and Resume from Jay Wright, 2000 (5, 3, 11)
        This folder contains a request from Jay Wright to give a poetry reading at Sweet Briar College, as well as his resume.
      - Vinay Dharwadker Information and Correspondence, 2001 (5, 3, 12)
        This folder includes an essay, correspondence, and a brochure for the Center for East Asian Studies at the University of Virginia that are from or regard Vinay Dharwadker.
      - Information and Correspondence on Artist Ambreen Butt, 2002 (5, 3, 13)
        This folder includes materials about artist Ambreen Butt and his work.
      - Rita Dove Correspondence, 2002-2003 (5, 3, 14)
        This folder contains party invitations, a family newsletter, and an email from poet Rita Dove. A letter from Vazirani to Dove is also included.
      - Profiles on Ethelbert Miller and Austin Clark, 2003 (5, 3, 15)
        This folder includes brief profiles on Ethelbert Miller and Austin Clark.
        Note: Boxes 4 and 5 of this collection contain further materials and correspondence in a separate accession made by Ethelbert Miller.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1982-2003 (5, 3, 16)
        This folder contains a postcard and poem sent to Vazirani by Ethelbert Miller.
    Subseries 6: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (6)
    This sub-series contains a range of personal and professional letters, cards, and emails sent to Vazirani.
    - (6, 3)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2002 (6, 3, 16)
        This folder contains letters, cards, photographs, newspaper clippings, and emails relating to a variety of professional and personal issues postmarked to Vazirani in 2002.
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2003 (6, 3, 17)
        This folder contains letters, cards, photographs, newspaper clippings, and emails relating to a variety of professional and personal issues postmarked to Vazirani in 2003.
  Series 3: Personal and Professional Letters and Work
- Personal and Professional Letters and Work, 1985-2006
  This series is a separate accession within the larger Vazirani collection. It contains correspondence, poetry, a manuscript, and photographs sent by Vazirani to her friend and colleague, Ethelbert Miller. Also included are materials regarding her death and funeral collected by Miller.
    Subseries 1: Background on Miller
  - Background on Miller, 2003 (1)
    This sub-series contains background information on Ethelbert Miller.
    - (1, 4)
      - Ethelbert Miller Profiles and Poetry Reading Announcement, 2003 (1, 4)
        This folder contains two brief articles on Ethelbert Miller, as well as a promotional poster for a reading at Georgetown University.
    Subseries 2: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1985-2003 (2)
    This sub-series contains correspondence sent by Vazirani to Miller between 1985 and 2003. There are no documents dated between 1987 and 1989.
    - (2, 4)
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1985 (2, 4)
        This folder contains six letters from Vazirani to Miller. The first is an apology for missing a scheduled meeting, while the rest focus on recent events and the process of writing. Some letters include poems. Two of the letters are not dated, but have been kept with the contents of original folder in which they were received.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1986 (2, 4, 3)
        This folder contains four letters and a postcard from Vazirani to Miller. They include updates about her life and work. The last letter features four poems and expresses Vazirani's intent to study with poet Derek Walcott.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1990 (2, 4)
        This folder contains 11 letters and postcards, as well as a greeting card from Vazirani to Miller. The letters and cards vary in length, and include updates and information on Vazirani's life and work, as well as references to Miller's achievements as a writer.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1991 (2, 4, 5)
        This folder contains seven letters and postcards, a holiday greeting card, and a poem submitted to "Yaddo" from Vazirani to Miller in 1992. The letters and cards vary in length and include references to her life and work, as well as a birthday greeting for Miller.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1992 (2, 4, 6)
        This folder contains five letters and postcards and a Christmas card Vazirani sent to Miller in 1992. The letters vary in length and include details on her life and work. One is written on the back of a rejection letter from the Atlantic and is attached to a draft of a poem titled, "Sunday School."
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1993 (2, 4, 7)
        This folder contains eight letters, cards, and notes from Vazirani to Miller. The letters vary in length and include details on her life and work, along with a newspaper clipping of a photo. Several references are made to funding opportunities, as well as articles, magazines, and authors Miller sent to Vazirani or suggested to her.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1994 (2, 4, 8)
        This folder contains 18 letters, notes, and cards sent from Vazirani to Miller in 1994. The letters vary in length and include details on her life and work, a request for recommendations for applications to a workshop and graduate school at the University of Virginia, and congratulatory and birthday messages for Miller.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1995 (2, 4, 9)
        This folder contains four letters, a note, and a postcard from Vazirani to Miller. They vary in length and include information on her professional and personal lives, as well as references to Vazirani's divorce.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1996 (2, 4, 10)
        This folder contains six postcards, a letter, and a printed email sent by Vazirani to Miller in 1996. The cards, letter, and email are all rather brief and include references to publicity for "White Elephants," the Folger Shakespeare Reading event, a range of professional and personal information, and birthday and get well messages to Miller. Also included is a copy of a letter sent to Vazirani's "White Elephants" publisher, Beacon Press, as well as a response to an open teaching position at the University of Colorado.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1997 (2, 4, 11)
        This folder contains nine letters and faxes sent to Ethelbert Miller in 1997. Six of the items are copies of letters sent to and from the Folger Shakespeare Library, Carnegie Mellon University, San Francisco State University, Barnard College, and the University of Oregon regarding poetry readings and teaching positions. The two faxes and final letter included are addressed to Miller and relate to Vazirani's reading at the Folger Shakespeare Event.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 1998-2000 (2, 4, 12)
        This folder contains four brief postcards sent by Vazirani to Miller from 1998 to 2000. They make references to New Year's, travel plans, a poetry reading, and Valentine's Day.
      - Ethelbert Miller Correspondence, 2002-2003 (2, 4, 13)
        This folder contains two postcards from 2001 and a letter from 2003 sent by Vazirani to Miller. They include references to Vazirani's publishing efforts, works in progress, and travel plans.
    Subseries 3: Miscellaneous Professional Materials
  - Miscellaneous Professional Materials, 1989-2003 (3)
    This sub-series contains a range of Vazirani's professional work, including poetry, resumes, information on reading events, and a signed photograph.
    - (3, 5)
      - Photos of Reetika (Jordan) Vazirani (signed) sent to Ethelbert Miller, 1990-1991 (3, 5, 1)
        This folder includes two photographs of Vazirani: a signed professional headshot sent in 1990, and a photograph of her with her husband, John T. Jordan, in 1991.
      - Poetry Collected by Ethelbert Miller, undated (3, 5, 2)
        This folder contains a number of poems by Vazirani. They include a collection titled, "Inventing Maya Biswas, My Mother," and five copies of "White Elephants I," among others.